"心爱的 我的思念让所有的词汇都黯然失色"
Hever Castle Boleyn Family Home "Dear heart, I cannot say how much I miss you."
"我渴求 在那夜晚 依偎在爱人怀中"
"I wish myself, especially in the evening, in my sweetheart's arms..."
继续念
Pray. Continue.
"美丽的双乳让我忘情狂吻
"Whose pretty breasts I trust shortly to kiss.
"钝笔拙舌岂能表达看不见你的痛
"Neither tongue nor pen can express the hurt of not seeing you.
"唯一的宽慰就是颤抖的企盼下次约会
"The only compensation is the thrill of anticipating our next meeting.
"世上哪里有比挚爱情侣长相厮守
"For what joy in this world can be greater
更快乐的事？"
than to have the company of her who is the most dearly loved."
哦…
Well...
国王坦白了他对你的爱
the king is plainly in love with you.
难道你看不出来 侄女
Don't you see, niece,
这会让一个男人 随便一个男人
it makes a man any man
脆弱的不堪一击
extremely vulnerable.
你的想法是什么呢 爱女？
How do you like your charge, sweetheart?
我…
I...
一开始我承认我并不是特别喜欢
at first I confess I did not like it so much.
我对国王毫无意思
I did not care for the king.
但如今我…
But now I...
如今我…
now I...
安 别被自己的伪装愚弄 对你来说是明智的
anne, it would be wise for you not to be fooled by your own masquerade.
你的职责就是利用他的爱情 帮助我们排挤沃尔西
It is your duty to use his love to our advantage in supplanting wolsey.
主教大人是横在我们和自由之间的障碍
The cardinal stands between us and everything.
现在该你发挥能力给他致命一击了
And it is now in your power to do him a great hurt.
我们都希望你能这样做
And we expect you to do so.
我要直达巴黎去见弗朗西斯国王
I shall go straight to paris to meet king francis
重新为两位陛下拟定一份新的条约
and ratify the new treaty between your majesties
由于教皇做了皇帝的阶下囚
and since his holiness remains a prisoner of the emperor,
我已经召集各位主教在巴黎秘密开会
I have summoned a conclave of the cardinals to meet in paris.
这样一来 说服他们在教皇不得抽身的情况下
It will be little matter to persuade them,
授予我权限 也并非难事
in the absence of the pope, to grant me license and authority
把陛下的离婚大事做个了断
to make a final judgment on your majesty's annulment.
所有臣民都祈祷您一路顺风
You leave with our blessing.
对于预期的成功 主教大人
And with anticipation of your success, your eminence.
我们已经等得不耐烦了
For which we are most impatient.
我是陛下真诚而又谦卑的奴仆
I am your majesty's true and humble servant.
哦 我忘了
Oh, I forgot.
你得带一个人去
There is someone you should take.
他的名字叫托马斯-怀亚特
His name is thomas wyatt.
那个诗人？
The poet?
我不喜欢他
I don't like him.
我曾有一块本该属于我的"珠宝"
He once possessed a jewel I would have.
安女士 你在这里有何贵干？
Lady anne, what are you doing here?
我来求见陛下
I have an audience with his majesty.
一个像你这么愚昧的女孩 有什么可对国王说的？
What would a silly girl like you have to say to a king?
陛下
Your majesty.
告诉我他会成功
Tell me he'll succeed.
谁 宝贝？
Who, sweetheart?
沃尔西
Wolsey.
他会的 不是吗？他会得到离婚许可？
He will, won't he? He'll get an annulment?
他当然会的
Of course he will.
勿庸置疑
Don't you doubt it.
怎么了？
What is it?
- 这样不奇怪吗？- 奇怪？
- Is it not strange? - Strange?
如此重要的事情您却托付给一个奴仆
To trust so great a matter to just one servant,
不管他是谁
Whoever he is,
陛下您有上千名仆人 随时乐意为您赴汤蹈火
when your majesty has a thousand servants ready and willing to do your bidding
而且当您的幸福都悬于此事的定夺时…
and when your very happiness hangs upon this resolution.
我的爱人
my love.
这事不需要你操心
This should not concern you.
原谅我 我说了不该说的话
Forgive me. I spoke of things I should not.
不 不
No, no.
我允许你我之间要经常坦诚相待
I give you leave that we may always speak freely with each other,
诚实 坦白 真心实意
honestly, openly and with a true heart.
于我 这才是真爱的定义
For me that is the true definition of love.
恕我在这里见您 大使先生
Forgive me, ambassador, for receiving you here.
听候陛下的吩咐
I am at your majesty's disposal.
门多萨先生 请帮助我
Senor Mendoza. help me.
当然 我是陛下的人
Of course, I am your Majesty's
我要传信给皇上 我无路可走
I need to get a message to the Emperor. I have no other way.
沃尔西浏览过我所有的信
Wolsey opens all my letters.
现在我还知道他买通了 我手下的几个侍女做他的间谍
And now I know that he has turned several of my women into his spies.
用什么买通？
By what means?
用钱 或者更甚 她们告诉我 在性方面满足她们
By money or even, so they tell me, by granting them sexual favours.
仁慈的上帝 我能帮您什么？
Dear God. How can I help?
皇上是我们家族的家长
The Emperor is the head of my family.
我希望他知道 国王要同我离婚
I want hime to know that the King is trying to divorce me.
他不想公开此事 但已经差人办理了
He wants to keep it secret but he has already instigated proceedings.
不可能
It's impossible!
难道他不需要教皇的许可吗？
Surely he needs the Pope's permission?
但教皇还在被皇帝关押着
But the Pope is still the Emperor's prisoner.
门多萨先生
Senor Mendoza,
看在仁爱的耶稣救世主的份上 看在众神敬畏的份上
for the love of our saviour, Jesus Christ, and the love of all that is sacred.
告诉我的侄儿我在这里所受的冷遇
tell my nephew what is being done to me here!
包在我身上了
Leave it to me.
我会想方设法避开主教的眼线的
I will find a way to evade the Cardinal's spies.
谢谢
Gracias.
(卡普顿·威纳茨 沃里克郡)
你在想什么？
What are you thinking about?
我不是在想
I wasn't thinking.
我在听
I was listening.
你在做新的曲子？
You're working on something new?
在摸索一些我需要听到的东西
To work on something I have to hear it.
我爱你
I love you.
那你的妻子怎么办？
What about your wife?
你很清楚她不是我的妻子
You know very well she's not my wife.
我从不相信爱情要落入教条的窠臼
I've never believed that love should be bound by doctrine.
我要走了
I'm going away.
你要走了？为什么？
You're going away? Why?
红衣主教沃尔西要去法国
Cardinal wolsey is going to france.
他邀我前去 与其他音乐家同行
He invited me to go with him. With other musicians.
你必须要去？
Must you go?
你应当清楚
You know very well that
主教之令犹如国王之令
an invitation from a cardinal is like an invitation from a king.
就算让我们这些小人物手入火盆 我们也只能"赴汤蹈火"
We little people must put our hands into the fire if we are "invited" to.
我会想你的
I'll miss you.
不 你不会的
No you won'T.
你很快就会移情别恋
You'll soon find other distractions.
告诉我真话 这趟出访你有何希望？
Tell me truthfully: What are your hopes for this mission?
我有很多希望
I have many hopes.
首先 治愈多年来阿拉贡法兰西 你敌我对所留下的创伤
Firstly, to heal the wounds caused by years of anglo-french hostility.
然后在谋取欧洲大陆新的权力平衡
And then to work towards a new balance of power in europe.
罗马之洗劫 教皇之囚牢
The sacking of rome, the imprisonment of the pope.
这些都动摇了整个欧洲
These things have destabilized the whole of europe.
还有教派？
And the church?
教派亦需调解
The church is also in need of mediation.
特别秘密枢机会议上 我们将为教会理事会出谋划策…
At the special conclave we shall lay plans for a general council which
在教皇缺席的情况下… 处理异端和改革这些当务之急
in the absence of the pope will deal with the pressing matters of heresy and reform.
国王的事情呢？
And the king's matter?
此事也将处理 不过只是众多议题之一
That will also be dealt with but as one of a number of other matters.
你认为其他主教会授权予你 解决此事吗？
Do you think the cardinals will give you the authority to deal with it?
是的
Yes.
那么您就是事实上的教皇
Then you will be de facto pope.
既然那厢教皇不可能释放俘虏…
And since his holiness may never escape captivity...
真是无稽之谈
this is idle speculation.
我还有事要做 托马斯大人
I have work to do, sir thomas.
你为何坐在黑暗之中？
Why are you sitting in the darkness?
出什么事了？
What's wrong?
你不懂的
You don't understand.
我当然懂
Of course I do!
我是你的哥哥 不是吗？
I'm your brother, aren't I?
你还是当初的你吗？
If only you were still as you used to be.
我记得我毫无保留地告诉你
I remember I told you everything.
- 我的秘密 - 你依然可以告诉我
- All my secrets. - You can still tell me.
- 不能 - 为什么？
- I can'T. - Why?
你泄漏给他人了
You'd share them.
法国 巴黎 国王弗朗西斯-瓦卢瓦的宫殿
The Palace of King Francis of Valois Paris, France
陛下
Your majesty.
我们向您致敬 和蔼的主教大人
We salute you, cardinal pacificus.
也是和平使者
Cardinal of peace.
我亲爱的主教大人
Mon cher cardinal.
我的朋友来了 哈哈
Mon ami, venez! Ha!Ha!
我的兄弟
Mon frere.
您能加入我们是多么荣幸之事
C'est bon de vous avoir parmi nous.
主教大人
Eminence.
见到您很高兴 夫人
Enchante, madame!
您如阳光一般美丽依旧
As beautiful as ever, like the sun.
您如此的亲切 主教大人
You are very gracious, monsieur le cardinal.
- 好像法国男人一样 - 就是
- Comme un homme francais! - Et voila.
我们待您如兄长 因此您就是
And we treat you as a brother, for that is what you are:
法兰西真诚尊贵的朋友
A true and loyal friend of france.
我们欢迎您…
We welcome you...
和你的随从 欢迎来到宫廷 奉上我们诚挚的心意
and all those with you, into our court and into our hearts.
我真是三生有幸 陛下
I am greatly honoured, your majesty.
而且感动非常
And very touched.
- 塔利斯 - 怀亚特先生
- Tallis. - Mr. Wyatt.
我一直在想
I've been thinking.
也许您能为我的诗谱一支曲子
Perhaps you would set a poem of mine to music.
我很荣幸 你已有成品？
I would be honoured. Do you have one ready?
我在酝酿一首呢 第一句有了
I'm working on one. I have the first line.
然后文思泉涌了
Then you have almost everything!
- 日安 主教大人 - 日安 殿下
- Bonjour, monsieur le cardinal. - Bonjour, your grace.
奥尔良公爵很高兴和玛丽公主订婚
The duke of orleans is very glad to be betrothed to princess mary.
我非常乐意
I am very happy.
- 好样的 我的儿子 - 好样的
- Bravo mon fils! - Bravo!
你对法国没多少好感吧 托马斯阁下
You don't like the french much, do you, sir thomas?
也没什么成见 怀亚特先生
I don't mind them, mr. Wyatt.
只是 他们总是那么的…
It's just that they're always so very...
法国特色
french.
有我的信吗
Were there any letters for me?
没有 夫人
No letters, madam.
安女士
Lady anne!
在 皇后陛下…
Yes, your majesty...
我知道你在做什么
I know what you are doing.
别想将国王从我身边夺走
But do not think to take the king away from me.
让他和你寻欢作乐 让他…
Let him play with you. Let him...
馈赠你礼物
give you gifts.
但他不可能对你一片真心
But he cannot give you his true heart
因为他的心属于我
for I have that in my keeping.
红衣主教沃尔西阁下的信
Letters from his eminence cardinal wolsey.
陛下理应知道 克莱蒙教皇圣人
Your majesty should know that his holiness, pope clement,
已经逃出了天使堡
has escaped from the castle sant'angelo.
他逃跑了？
He's escaped?
显然他装扮成老盲人 蒙骗过了追捕者
Apparently he dressed as an olblind man, and walked out past his captors.
此刻他身居何处？
Where is he now?
据在下所知 他在意大利的奥维多城
According to my information, in an italian town called orvieto,
藏身于他的宫廷仅存的当地主教殿内
in the bishop's palace there, with what remains of his court.
当然 他仍在省罗马皇帝的控制范围之内
Of course, he is still within the power of the emperor.
然而他自由了？
And yet he is free?
有否可能…
It would be possible...
有否可能派人去他那里？
it would be possible to send someone to him?
给他带个口信？
To give him a message?
当然没问题
Indeed it would be possible.
你如何得悉这些？沃尔西告诉你的？
How do you know all this? From wolsey?
不是 陛下 我有自己的耳目
No, majesty. I have my own sources.
那么托人带话给教皇
Let us say I wanted a message carried to his holiness.
你能找到人吗？一个足以让你托付性命的人？
Do you know someone? Someone you could trust with your life?
牧师兼外交官奈特博士 他是个地道忠心的英国人
Dr.Knight.A man of god. A diplomat.And a true englishman.
带他来见我
Bring him to me.
约克-托马斯-沃尔西大主教的地租负债
Debts owning for land rental deu to the Archbishop, Thomas Wolsey of York
原来如此
So that's how he does it!
叫牌
Call.
一对王后 我赢了
My 2 queens win.
我痛恨打牌
I hate cards!
我痛恨皇宫
I hate this court.
我甚至痛恨时间本身
I even hate time itself.
陛下 能听在下一言吗？
Your majesty, might I make a suggestion?
但说无妨
Anything.
将皇宫抛到一边吧
Forget the court.
我们去森林打猎
Let's go to the woods. Let's go for a hunt,
象往常那样驰骋
as we used to do.
对 对
Yes! Yes!
但不带布兰登
But not brandon.
- 查尔斯是你的朋… - 我不能原谅萨福克勋爵
- Charles is your... - I haven't forgiven my lord suffolk.
我无法原谅他
I can't forgive him.
他未经应允擅自迎娶我的王妹
He never asked permission to marry my sister.
这… 不可一世 让人忍无可忍
It'S... insufferable arrogance!
他到底意欲如何？
I mean, what did he expect?
听着…
Look...
我不是要将他永世逐出宫外…
I don't mean that he's banished forever...
就今生今世而已
just as long as he breathes!
来吧
Come on.
知道我们该干什么吗？
You know what we should do?
- 干什么？亲爱的？- 野餐
- What, sweetheart? - Have a picnic.
在康普顿的领地
At compton's place.
警惕周围动静
Keep your eyes open.
欢迎围捕
Welcome round!
你看 威廉 一切早已事过境迁
You see william: Things can never be as they used to be!
托马斯-博林爵士大人
Sir thomas boleyn, your grace.
- 大人… ？- 大人
- My lord...?! - Your grace.
我何德何能得您的到访？
To what do I owe this pleasure?
能容我直言吗？
May I speak frankly?
祝你健康 大人
To your health, my lord.
也祝你健康
And yours.
诺福克派我来
Norfolk has sent me.
可诺福克恨我
But norfolk hates me.
毕竟我初来乍到 而他高高在上 对我不屑一顾
I am a new man, after all. And he is far too grand for me.
我怀疑出于同样的理由 他鄙视我们所有人
I suspect he despises us all for the same reasons.
然而他原意庇护我们 及其他人
And yet he has interests to protect and further, like the rest of us.
既然他找上门来 就要和我们有所礼尚往来
He must deal with us as he finds us.
毕竟 还有人让他恨之入骨
And, after all, there is someone he hates even more.
- 红衣主教 - 毋庸置疑
- The cardinal. - Of course.
但又与我何干？
But what is that to me?
怀念宫廷生活吗 大人？
Do you miss the court, your grace?
也许不
Perhaps you don'T.
在这片绿色的大地上 你可以尽情享受闲暇时光
Down here, in this green space, you have so much leisure to enjoy.
如此多庸庸碌碌的追逐
So many idle pursuits.
然而我却听人说 国王的毗邻宛似太阳
And yet I have heard it said by some that the king's presence is like the sun
当你远离阳光
and when you are away from it,
便只剩下茫茫无边的黑夜
there is only eternal night.
你是个聪明人 博林
You're a clever man, boleyn.
人们都说
That is what people say.
说你魅力焕发 足智多谋
They say you are charming and clever.
诺福克有何企图？
What does norfolk want?
他希望你帮助我们除掉沃尔西
He wants you to help us destroy wolsey.
作为报答 他会劝说国王原谅你
And in return, he will persuade the king to forgive you
并迎你回宫
and welcome you back to court.
多谢你 大人
Thank you, my lord.
你听到了什么？
What did you hear?
一字不漏
Everything.
你会怎么办？
What will you do?
我该怎么办？
What should I do?
你曾说 沃尔西有时待你非常和善
You once told me that sometimes wolsey had been kind to you.
是吗？
Did I?
我忘得七七八八了
I had quite forgotten.
陛下似乎堕入了情网
It seems our majesty is in love.
爵士
Sir.
可怜的哈利
Poor harry.
塔利斯… ？
Tallis...?
什么事？
What is it?
你该死的诗人从不睡觉吗？
You bloody poets never sleep?
我写了几行
I've written the first few lines.
可以读给你听吗？
Can I read them to you?
"他们弃我而去 可我却赤脚"
"They flee from me that sometime did me seek.
"踱步在空荡的房间 自处寻觅"
"With naked foot, stalking in my chamber.
"我曾见他们温柔驯良"
"I have seen them gentle, tame, and meek,
"如今却狂野不羁"
"that are now wild,
"全然忘却自己曾不顾一切危险"
"and do not remember "that sometime they put themselves in danger
"从我手心获取食粮"
"to take bread at my hand;
"如今他们到处漫游 永无休止地寻求改变… "
"and now they range busily seeking with a continual change..."
- 就写了这么点 - 写得很精彩
- that's all there is so far. - It's wonderful.
字里行间充满了韵律
There is music in it.
是关于什么的？
What's it about?
- 一个姑娘 - 什么姑娘？
- A girl. - What girl?
我们就称她棕发姑娘吧
Let's just call her the brunette.
我一度爱过她
I loved her once.
觉得她也爱过我
And I thought she loved me.
可现在她已属他人？
But now she belongs to another?
小伙子们 安静点
Boy! Quiet in here!
或许她只是寻常姑娘
She may be just a girl,
可我告诉你 塔利斯先生
but I tell you this mr. Tallis:
一旦让她达到她的目的
If she gets her way,
会让整个国家而咆哮
she will set our whole country in a roar.
晚上好 主教大人
Bonsoir, excellence.
谢谢
Thank you.
陛下想确保阁下能得到一切所需
His majesty wants assurance that your eminence has everything you desire.
原谅我
Forgive me.
如果我年轻一点愚昧一点 或是精力旺盛一点
If I was younger, or more foolish, or more alive...
我会欣然接受
I would gladly take this offer.
你美极了 小姐
Tu es trop belle, mademoiselle.
不值得被他人如娼妇般利用
You deserve better than to be used as a whore.
晚安 主教大人
Bonne nuit, excellence.
众位 皇后驾到
My lords and ladies, the queen.
皇后陛下
Your majesty.
大人
Your grace.
女王陛下
Majesty.
- 达比大人 - 我的皇后
- Lord darby. - My queen.
我有东西给你
I have something for you.
看见了吗？
You see?
猎鹰是你的羽饰
The falcon is your crest...
石榴则归她所有
and the pomegranate is hers!
你还是不明白 对吗？
You still don't understand, do you?
这不是游戏 乔治 这里危机四伏
It's not a game, george. It's dangerous!
博林女士
Mistress boleyn.
- 克伦威尔先生 - 我带来了消息
- Mr. Cromwell. - I have some news.
国王派了个好手 持离婚信函去见教皇
The king is dispatching a good man to see the pope, with letters about the divorce.
奈特博士
A dr.Knight.
我认识奈特博士 他是我的辅导教师
I know dr.Knight. He was my tutor.
的确
Indeed.
一切事物都相互关联…
All things connect...
女士们
ladies.
先生
Sir.
我猜你们是皇后陛下的宫女？
Would I be right to think you are maids of honour to her majesty?
是的 先生
Yes, sir.
乔治-博林
George boleyn.
你们此刻不认识我 但总有认识我的一天
You don't know me now, but one day you will.
- 我们可以互捞好处 - 愿闻其详
- We could be useful to each other. - How so?
告诉我你们在跟谁上床
You tell me who you're fucking,
然后我再表达意见
and I'll tell you if it's a good idea.
明白了吗？
You understand?
我们有什么报酬？
And in return?
我会想出来的
I'll think of something.
就看你们对功名利禄有多么饥渴
It depends how hungry you are to be rich and famous.
我可以妥善做出安排
It's something I can arrange.
我能创造财富
I'm a builder of fortunes.
拿着
Here!
全靠你了 奈特博士
We rely upon you, dr.Knight,
将这两封信送到奥维多的教皇手上
to deliver these 2 bulls to his holiness, at orvieto.
我们的亲笔书信
They were written by our own hand.
陛下
Majesty.
眼下若跟圣罗马皇帝讲和 对欧洲大有好处
It would be better for europe if we now make peace with the emperor.
你胆敢这样说 ？
How can you say that?!
他让我成为阶下囚 亲手捏了我的睾丸
He made me his prisoner! He squeezed my balls!
还索取我百万赎金
I had to pay him millions in ransom.
我的长子仍是他阶下囚
And my eldest son is still his captive.
我怎能跟这个混账讲和
How can I make peace with that piece of shit!
发展到这一步 您一定感到心满意足
You must be gratified by the progress you've made so far.
老实说 我已风烛残年
To be honest, it's something of a burden dragging my old
往返国与国之间已成负担
cracked body from country to country.
您宁愿返回家园
You'd rather be at home.
想到我不在时 国王会受他人影响 我就感到忧心忡忡
I do fret rather that the king will be influenced by others in my absence.
经过这次秘密枢机会议 您勿需烦恼
After the conclave, you need not fret.
很快您就有权取悦他了
You'll soon have the power to please him.
晚安 大人
Good evening my lord.
谢谢
Thank you.
衣童…
Boy...!
衣童？
Boy?!
去你的
Damn you!
国王驾到
The king!
亲爱的安
Sweet anne.
皇后驾到
The queen!
不 不 等等
No, no! Wait!
只需片刻
Only a moment.
今晚我将和你的父亲和叔父共进晚餐
Tonight I dine with your father and uncle.
陛下 我父亲自认受宠若惊
Your majesty, my father says it is all beyond his deserving.
不 与他们相处 拉近你我之间的距离
No, for when I am with them, I am close to you.
给
Here.
另一个表达我爱慕之情的信物
Another token of my affection.
请收下
Take it.
你卑微仆人的献礼
From your humble servant.
你的脖颈
Your neck.
我喜欢你的脖颈
I love your neck.
大人们 在此为我们心头大事的解决
My lords, let us drink to the resolution of the matter
干杯
which is uppermost in our minds.
- 陛下请 - 陛下请
- Your majesty. - Majesty.
不久之后 我们就能得到答复
In a very short while we shall have an answer.
比起红衣主教沃尔西 将此事托付给奈特博士让我更加放心
I would trust to hear it more from dr.Knight than cardinal wolsey.
为什么这么说？
Why do you say?
我担心此事成功与否 并未关系到主教大人的利益
I fear it is not in the cardinal's interest to succeed.
但是他的利益和我的利益 不是相辅相成的吗？
But surely his interest and mine are one and the same?
他是我的仆人
He is my servant.
大人他的意思是红衣主教 对我的女儿有些许偏见
His grace means that the cardinal has some prejudice against my daughter.
我知道 我知道
I know. I know.
他称她为愚昧的姑娘
He called her a silly girl.
她跟我说了
She told me.
还有一件事情
There is another matter.
大人他没想告诉你 但是
My lord did not want to tell you, but
我认为这件事情陛下您需要知晓
it is something I think your majesty should be made aware of.
说啊？
Well?
陛下
Majesty,
在您的眷顾下我被亲典为 陛下您的皇室财政审计大臣
by your great bounty I was appointed comptroller of your majesty's household.
由于此职位 让我可以…
And in such a capacity, I have...
我发现 当腐败的修道院被关闭的时候
I have discovered that, when corrupt religious houses are closed down,
他们的财产并未按照规矩转入国库
instead of all their assets going to your exchequer, as they should do,
反而通常被转到他处
they are often diverted elsewhere.
转去哪里？
Elsewhere?
转入了沃尔西的私人基金
Into wolsey's private foundations.
用于他在牛津的大学建立
Into the creation of his great college at oxford.
我不得不承认 你们的揭发让我倍感震惊
I must admit, I find your intimations shocking.
确切的说 让我心痛
Indeed, I am hurt.
红衣主教沃尔西不单是我的议政大臣
Cardinal wolsey is not only my chancellor,
还一直都是我的朋友
he has always been my friend.
陛下 一个真诚和衷心的朋友
In this world, majesty, a true and loyal friend
是一个男人在此世界里能得到的最大恩惠
is the greatest boon any man can have.
而其他人… 总是会有 顾己弃主的怪习惯
For in everything else, there is a strange habit of forsaking.
说到这儿我想起来 萨福克公爵来见过我
That reminds me, the duke of suffolk came to see me.
布莱顿？
Brandon?
他说 他将手膝着地爬过来 以求得陛下您的原谅
He said he would crawl on his hands and knees to beg your majesty's forgiveness.
那条项链 是谁给你的？
That necklace. Who gave it to you?
回答我
Answer me.
是陛下给的
His majesty.
你出价不低 嗯？
You are expensive, uh?
你这个昂贵的妓女
an expensive Whore!
我不是什么妓女…
I am no whore...
陛下
your majesty.
我爱着国王陛下 我相信陛下他也爱着我
I love his majesty. I believe he loves me.
他不过如男人为新事物着迷一样 被你冲昏了头脑
He is infatuated by you, as men often are by new things.
很快他会看到你真正的一面
Soon he will see you for what you really are!
然后厌倦你…
And he will tire of you...
正如厌倦其他女人一般
like all the others!
如果他不会厌倦我呢？
And what if he does not?
我可没准许你开口讲话
I did not give you permission to speak!
你只是个贱婢
You are a servant!
现在给我出去
Go now!
滚
Go!
法国 胡昂乡间
Countryside near Rouen, France
驻步 驻步
Au pas! Au pas!
喝喝… …
Whoa!...
成列驻足
En ligne!
你是谁
Who are you?
奈特博士 请原谅我们冒然打扰
Dr.Knight? Forgive us, sir.
我们必须请您在旅途中忙里偷闲一两天
We must just ask you to break off your journey for a day or two.
怎么可能 我在为国王办事
Impossible! I am on the king's business.
的确 先生 我们也知晓
Yes, sir, we know that.
那就是为和您必须和我们走一趟
That is why you must come with us.
啊 奈特博士 请进
Ah, dr.Knight. Come in.
主教大人 我…
Your eminence, I...
我的事务就是要了解国王的事务
I make it my business to know the king's business.
你真以为能在我毫无知晓的情况下 就送信到奥维多？
Did you really think you could go to orvieto without my knowing all about it?
你被命护送着两封御书给教皇 对吗？
Now, you've been sent by the king to the pope with these 2 bulls, is that correct?
是的
Yes.
这两封可是非比寻常的文书
They are quite extraordinary documents.
你可知里面是什么内容？
Do you know what is in them?
略有所知
Yes. A little.
那你还同意护送着两封信？
And you still agreed to carry them?
第一封文书请求教皇本人 批准他离婚
The first document asks the pope to permit him once divorced
并迎娶任何一位得他钟爱的女人…
to marry any woman he chooses...
即使由于她的一亲属与国王的旧事
even one who would normally be forbidden to him
让她在常理下禁止与国王结婚
because of a prior relationship to one of her relatives!
我不理解国王何以写此种书信？
I don't understand. The king wrote this.
他所暗指的女人到底是谁？
What woman is he referring about?
安-博林女士
Mistress anne boleyn.
安-博林？
Anne boleyn?
国王爱的是安-博林？
The king loves anne boleyn?
是的 大人
Yes, sir.
那他所提到的那段"旧事"指的是什么？
And what is this prior relationship he refers to?
主教大人您肯定知道…
Surely your eminence is aware that
陛下和安的姐姐玛利有过男女关系
his majesty had carnal relations with anne's older sister, mary.
甚至和她们的母亲都曾经云雨过
Perhaps even with their mother.
但这都是传言 我并不会听信
So it is rumoured. I give it no credence.
我是指关于她们母亲的传闻…
With regard to the mother.
那么第二封书信 你看过了吗？
And the second document. Have you read it?
没有 大人
No, sir.
与之前一封如出一辙
About just as well.
我可不想将此信呈给
I wouldn't like to be the man that has to present this
圣-彼得的传人
to the descendant of saint peter.
上面请求到"如果您无法废除我的婚姻"
It asks this: "If no way can be found to nullify the king's marriage...
"那么教皇理当批准他去娶第二个妻子"
" then the pope should simply allow him to take a second wife.
你明白了吗？他要求教皇批准重婚之罪
Do you understand? He's asking the pope to sanction bigamy!
既然是国王下令的 你还是上路吧 奈特博士
Since the king commands it, you must be on your way, dr.Knight.
但是别指望能成功 更别提得到任何荣誉
But with no hope of success... or honour.
我听说你如狗一般爬过来
I heard you crawled here like a dog!
差不多… 管住你的舌头
Something like. Hold your tongue!
你一直都善用自己的花言巧语
You were always too useful with it.
是的 陛下
Yes, your majesty.
你是来乞求我的原谅？
Have you come to beg my forgiveness?
是的 陛下
Yes, your majesty.
那就求我
Well then beg for it.
我以我的心 我的灵魂
With all my heart. With all my soul.
以我生命的每一分毫
With every ounce of my being.
向我的国王 我的君主 我令人畏惧的主子
My king, my sovereign, my dread lord,
乞求您原谅这位可怜的仆人
I beg you to forgive your miserable servant,...
您的卑微 毫无价值 不知事前深思的仆人
your humble, worthless, thoughtless servant,
这位不配接受您的恩赐及您的眷顾
who deserved so little and by your bounty and your grace,
却又蒙受恩宠的仆人
was given so much.
我这样知恩不报龌蹉下流之徒
Ungrateful wretch that I am.
不配陛下您的宠爱
Unworthy of your majesty's love.
过来
Come here!
如果你能击败我 你就可以重返宫廷
If you can beat me, you can come back to court.
准备好了吗？
Ready?
欢迎回来
Welcome back.
- 那我又能怎么办？- 我不知道
- What was I supposed to do? - I don't know.
但我与您有同感 此书信的确粗鲁不可接受
But I agree with you. It was crude and unacceptable.
- 我对陛下深感失望 - 托马斯 我必须问你
- I'm disappointed in his majesty. - Thomas, I have to ask you this.
你会接受红衣主教教会的合议吗
Will you accept the judgment of the cardinals?
现在这又有何所谓？
What does it matter now?
教皇已经是自由之身
The pope is free.
无须枢机会议的参与
There is no need for a conclave.
不 此时此刻更加需要
There is more need than ever.
教皇依旧在圣罗马帝国的控制中
The pope is still in the power of the emperor,
无法执行任何对教会的控制
unable to exercise any control over the church.
所以必须有其他人接手 我再次问你
So someone else must do so and I ask you again,
你可否会顺从红衣主教教会的合议？
will you accept the judgment of the cardinals?
甚者…
More...
如果你不赞同我 那么你就是在反对我
if you are not for me now, then you are against me.
形势越发的危急
The stakes have grown higher.
克伦威尔先生告诉我 国王与诺福克及博林共进晚餐
Mr. Cromwell tells me that the king now dines with norfolk and boleyn.
他们可都是我的死敌 他们一直都寻求机会让我下台
They are my bitter enemies. They constantly seek my downfall.
如果你不帮助我 那你就是在帮他们
And if you do not help me, then you help them.
我需要提醒你:
And need I remind you of this:
你的步步高升都是我的功劳
You owe all your advancement in this world to me.
托马斯 我们相识以久
Thomas, we've known each other a long time.
我知道你对我的处事手段及我的行为而抱怨
I know you've often complained about my methods, my way of dealing, but
但将这些置之度外 相信你我之间依旧有很多共同之处
underneath all of that, I believe we still share many things.
即使全世界在抨击我们的信仰 逼迫我们妥协
We're still humanists, even though the world batters our beliefs,
我们始终都是人道主义者
and compromises our actions.
没有任何事情
Well nothing.
这世上没有任何事情 甚至没有任何一位王公
No earthly thing, not even a prince
能够让我将信仰妥协
will ever compromise mine.
哦 我明白
Oh, I see.
你不想深陷泥潭 我理解
You don't want to get your hands dirty. I understand, well,
但不幸的是 你没得选
unfortunately, you don't have a choice.
染坊工的双手总会被他的工作原料而浸染
The dyer's hand is always stained by the elements he works with.
这就是我的原料
Here is my element.
精神之元素
The spiritual element.
高层次的元素
The higher element.
现在你说说看: 我有被它玷污吗？
Now you tell me: Am I stained by it?
红衣主教们到的时候知会我一声
Let me know the moment the cardinals arrive.
法国国王陛下驾到
Sa majeste le roi de france.
我亲爱的沃尔西
Mon cher wolsey,
我来此是告诉您
I expect you heard.
红衣主教们不会来了
The cardinals are not coming.
我无能为力
There's nothing I can do about it.
他们只听从教皇的指令
They only take orders from his holiness.
时过境迁 我的朋友
The wheel turns my friend.
"他们弃我而去 可我却赤脚"
"They flee from me, that sometime did me seek,
"踱步于房间内 四处寻觅"
with naked foot, stalking in my chamber...
"若非上苍 此刻已百般恩爱 美好万分"
"thanks be to fortune, it has been otherwise "twenty times better
"但是曾经一度恍然"
"but once in special,
"在芊薄玲珑 悦目的装扮下"
"in thin array, after a pleasant guise,
"当她宽松的衣袍自细肩滑落"
"when her loose gown from her shoulders did fall,
"她将我环抱在纤细的手臂中"
"and she caught me in her arms long and small,
"一边甜蜜的轻吻着我 一边低柔的话道"
"therewith all sweetly did me kiss, and softly said:
"亲爱的心上人 你可否倾心于此？"
"Dear heart how like you this?"
主教大人 您能保佑我的女儿吗？
Your eminence, your blessing on my daughter?
- 上帝保佑你 我的孩子 - 感谢您 主教大人
- Blessings, my child. - Thank you, your eminence.
- 主教大人 可否占用您些许时间？- 不可 不可
- Your eminence, if you please a moment. - No, no.
- 克伦威尔先生 - 主教大人
- Mr. Cromwell. - Your eminence.
- 国王正在等候您 但是… - 但是什么？
- The king waits you but... - but what?
他并非一个人
He is not alone.
陛下…
Majesty...
怎样… ？
well...?
陛下 我本以为能够…
Majesty, I... I was hoping that...
你可以在博林女士面前畅言
you can speak freely in front of mistress boleyn.
她知晓一切
She knows everything.
那么
So!
你从巴黎归来
You've come back from paris!
是的
Yes.
跟我们讲讲你的凯旋而归
Tell us of your triumphs!
讲讲你的好消息
Tell us all your news.
我们迫切的想听到
We are so eager to hear.
哦 神人眷顾之人…
Oh for the love of god man,
我可否离婚？
do I have my divorce?
陛下可还记得 我去巴黎…
Your majesty will recall that I went to paris...
"没有梦想"
it was no dream.
"我神志清醒的舒展而卧"
I lay broad waking.
"但我的温情突然之间"
But all is turned, through my gentleness,
"招来了挥之而去的遗弃"
into a strange fashion of forsaking.
"而我却要为她的安逸远走高飞"
And I have leave to go of her goodness.
"既然我被如此冷善的对待"
But since that I so kindly am served
"我想知道 她又配得到什么？"
I'd like to know what she has deserved!